<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Marcin Halupka</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Marcin Halupka</description>
    <image>
      <url>%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 17:15:59 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Item to Item Collaborative Filtering</title>
      <link>/posts/item-to-item-collaborative-filtering/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 17:15:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/item-to-item-collaborative-filtering/</guid>
      <description>Recommendation algorithms are best known for their use on e-commerce Websites where they use input about a customer&amp;rsquo;s interest to generate a list of recommended items. Many applications use only the items that customers purchase and explicitly rate to represent their interests but they can also use other attributes, including items viewed, demographic data, subject interests and favorite artists.
In 2003 Amazon published an industry report presenting their approach to that topic back then, this post will be its summary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Mix Modeling</title>
      <link>/posts/marketing-mix-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 12:05:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/marketing-mix-modeling/</guid>
      <description>Marketing Mix Model or Media Mix Model (MMM) is used by advertisers to measure how their media spending contributes to sales. As a result, the future budget can be allocated in a more efficient way. ROAS - return on ad spend and mROAS - marginal return on ad spend are the key metrics to look at. High ROAS indicates the channel is efficient, high mROAS means that increasing spend in the channel will yield a high return based on current spending level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Series Visualization</title>
      <link>/posts/time-series-visualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 23:36:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/time-series-visualization/</guid>
      <description>The first thing to do in any data analysis is to plot the data. Graphs enable many features of the data to be visualized, including patterns, unusual observations, changes over time and relationships between the data. Just as the type of data determines what forecasting methods to use, it also determines what graphs are appropriate.
Ts objects A time series can be thought as a list of numbers, along with some information about what times those numbers were recorded.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Time Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>/posts/introduction-to-time-series-forecasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 23:35:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introduction-to-time-series-forecasting/</guid>
      <description>Good forecasts can seem almost magical, while bad forecasts may be dangerous. We can look at three famous predictions about computing:
 I think there is a world market for maybe five computers. (Chairman of IBM, 1943) Computers in the future may weigh no more than 1.5 tons. (Popular Mechanics, 1949) There is no reason anyone would want a computer in their home. (President, DEC, 1977)  The last of these was made three years before IBM produced the first personal computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forward and Backward Algorithm in Hidden Markov Model</title>
      <link>/posts/forward-and-backward-algorithm-in-hidden-markov-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/forward-and-backward-algorithm-in-hidden-markov-model/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Hidden Markov Model provided basic understanding of the topic. We also presented three main problems of HMM (Evaluation, Learning and Decoding). In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll deep dive into the Evaluation Problem. Starting from mathematical understanding, finishing on Python and R implementations.
Quick recap Hidden Markov Model is a Markov Chain which is mainly used in problems with temporal sequence of the data. Markov Model explaimns that the next step depends only on the previous step in a temporal sequence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Hidden Markov Model</title>
      <link>/posts/introduction-to-hidden-markov-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introduction-to-hidden-markov-model/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this post and series is to present the foundational concept, usability, intuition of the algorithmic part and some basic axamples of Hidden Markov Models. To understand the content, basic knowledge on probability should be sufficient.
Why kind of problems I can solve with them? The ones where we observe a sequential data but we suspect that behind the scenes there may be something going on that affects the sequence we are looking at.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
